We'll still be taking the one as they come.
So
town of Ann Arbor, special town meeting,
Tuesday, February 7, 7PM.
Kathy? Wally Barking.
Wally Wallace's I'll
>> second. Seconded by Joey Howell.
Any other nominations?
I
have a motion to close the nomination. No objection?
Okay.
Vote on the nomination. All in favor? Aye.
Aye. By showing hands and voice,
we have Wally Martin.
Wally?
Need a motion and a second on the item,
>> and then I'll turn the floor over to Eric to do the explanation
for the item.
>> So the first item,
Michelle Baton will be over financing purchase
Okay,
>> folks. Thank you all for coming out.
I'm gonna try to get through this as fast as I can. I'll answer any questions that you have
as soon as I get through with this.
So here's all four things we're voting on tonight. We're gonna talk right now about the first one.
And the first question is why are we asking you to buy plow truck?
So we, as a town in 2018,
did a pretty exhaustive study
about what the cheapest way to supply plow trucks to the town of Andover is.
We looked at a bunch of other states and a bunch of other municipalities
and we came to, like, four main conclusions.
The first is if we hold plow trucks longer than their optimal life, it costs us more than if we don't. So
using something for thirty years
when for the last ten, your maintenance costs are for the roof is just not an economical thing for the town to do.
The second thing is that the biggest thing that kills us is rust.
The third is that there's a big difference in manufacturers
in the total cost of ownership,
and buying a less expensive
vehicle up front
in the past a lot more money overall than spending the money upfront
to get a better quality vehicle.
And then the fourth conclusion is that the body rot
accounts for an awful lot of the cost and maintenance of these vehicles.
So
in
2018,
the CIP
approved and instituted a fifteen year equipment plan for public works
And the goal was right here,
to balance the cost, productivity, and reliability of the equipment.
And we looked at basically everything that public works had.
And one of things the that came out of it was that plow trucks are the single most expensive asset in public works.
So here's what we're trying to do to maximize the lifespan and minimize cost.
First is we purchase one truck every fifth year.
We have three primary
plow routes and that means each truck is used for fifteen years as a primary plow truck and then it goes into a reserve or a spare role for another five years. So we're anticipating,
you know, the the most cost effective way to do it is to use these trucks for about twenty years total.
The second thing is
with the last truck we bought and with this one, we've switched from regular mild steel bodies
to
hardox slash stainless steel bodies.
And we did this because we were getting about twelve years out of the old mild steel bodies.
Today, we were to rebody a truck.
It would cost us around $45,000
to buy the body and it's about another 20,000 to do the install,
presuming we don't have hydraulics.
So if you spend an extra $25,000
to buy a stainless body
and you don't have to replace it, overall, you save the town quite a bit of money.
The second thing is that all of these trucks get fluid film undercoated
every year before plow season.
Because one of the best things you can do is to prevent corrosion,
so they get basically,
completely washed and fluid coated every year.
The second thing is after every storm, every bit of salt gets unloaded from these vehicles and the vehicles get washed.
And if we have looks like we have a break storms, we usually power wash em.
Again, we're doing everything we can to prevent corrosion in the vehicles so we can run em as long as we can.
Now, with that,
we're still generally planning around year ten for these vehicles
of bringing them in, having the frames and bodies sandblasted
and repainted.
Again, the idea is to do lower cost items to extend the lives of them as much as possible.
So, this is what we have right now. You can see we're
not quite on plan maintaining
three vehicles
less than than fifteen years old.
But if you buy this next one, we'll basically be on cycle other than our emergency
going to be retiring
is a cloud truck that's already 26 years old.
So,
if we approve this by town meeting, what we're doing is we're authorizing the purchase of a Freightliner Plow truck with a Hardox Body Plow.
We're talking about five year loan payments of 58,970.45,
which if you notice from your sheet is slightly higher than what we originally allocated.
The manufacturer basically will give us a lock for thirty days at a time,
and so we had a lock the meeting but it expired before we can actually pull the trigger. So
as you know, the Fed's raised the interest rates again so that affects the cost of financing a little bit. So this will be the actual number that we will be paying.
So to get a billed slot,
because slots are
in such high demand,
they're
requiring us to put the first year's
to We're
get
the of
>> the
rotation.
So we're paying for this with the Public Works Equipment Fund,
and that is a permanent fund
that we put money into annually,
and we fund it basically level funding every year, and we spend out of it as we can.
Because the Cloudtrucks
is basically two and a half years worth of funding and that fund can't buy it all at once, so in this case we're financing this over a five year period.
So this is the actual question,
and that is the correct dollar amount that we will be
paying the vendor.
So what are your questions?
Shoot. So
and there's another mic right over there.
>> If this is the question that we approve,
let's say that
once we get audited,
if we have money on Bloomberg,
is there a possibility that we could pay this off to save the interest?
Because the interest is fairly substantial.
>> Sure. Is that an option if we approve it the way the question is? That's my question.
>> So
I think if we sign this agreement,
you know, we're signing this agreement to lease the vehicle.
So no, I'm not sure we can go back and just outright purchase.
But I also don't think we're gonna have enough on expended funding to do it anyway. So I think it's kind of a moot point.
Yeah. Questions? Microphone's
>> right up there, sir. I don't need How
many miles do you put on these trucks a year?
>> We don't put a ton of miles on these trucks, not by any means. I think
I can't tell you off the top of my head, but it's not the miles that kills us. It's corrosion. Right? I know. And I I don't know why you don't piggyback off the state and get it international.
So
we have one international right now.
That international,
we have spent about a $130,000
in repairs since we've owned that vehicle.
That has been a spectacularly
unreliable
vehicle,
and the reason we're not going for internationals
>> is because their cost to repair has been historically very high. I mean, I just can't see it. You got a guy I don't know if it's even a bolt in Delvernay.
He's had the same Ford truck for thirty years,
and he uses that a lot more than this town.
>> But it's not a plow. What's
that? I don't think it's a plow. He doesn't garage it. He doesn't wash it like the town does. But is it a plow truck? No. It spawns you a lot. Listen now. These guys wash their truck after every storm. There's
No. No. It's it's bigger. It's a
>> Six fifty? I mean, what It's it's quite a bit bigger than a six fifty. You don't know what it is? I mean The Ford Louisville is the one that is being replaced. The Ford Louisville, you know what size Louisville is? It's
it's a 28,000 pound. It's a What's the GVW of this new truck? It's about the same thing. It's about a 28,000 pound GVW truck.
Just seems like the truck is over $300,000.
I don't know we're gonna pay $300,000
for a truck.
That's what they owe.
We're gonna lease it and not own it.
No. It's no. So so A lease to buy. Yeah. It's a lease to buy. So it's five payments and we own it. We'll own it at five payments.
Right. We're not leasing it and giving it back. We we make five payments five years in a row. Lease it to own? Yeah. It's a lease to own. So they all they're doing is basically instead of the town making a payment every month, we make payment once a year. Yeah. So five payments, we own it, and then it's ours. So
>> Right. Yeah. We're not giving it back at the end of five years. We own that a year.
>> Don? Yeah. No. No. They'll be website drive. What what condition
>> It's
in pretty good condition.
I mean, it's definitely a saleable vehicle.
It's pretty underpowered.
We did a fair amount of work on it this year. We had some injector issues that we solved.
So it's road worthy? Is it snowplow vehicle currently?
>> Yeah. It's it's still functioning. It's still what we run as an emergency spare, short.
>> And what what is the fund balance in the
quote works?
We have a little fund right now. I think there's roughly 45,000
>> left in that fund.
So we're gonna take that and we're gonna basically use use contingency for the remainder to come up to the
the actual purchase price of the vehicle.
And how much money do we yearly put into the
Quilt Forks Capital Equipment Fund?
We've been funding that at around a $100,000
a year.
I mean, it's up to the board of finance what that exact number is, but year in year out, we've been putting about a $100,000. This this past year, this past budget we put a 100,000 the into the capital?
>> Find on the town's website with regard to the status of any of the funds. So, I'm going have the same question with regard to all four of the questions
that are posed for tonight is how much
is currently in the funds and how much have we expended in this budget year. So, the most recent that I could find on the website was from October of last year
in which we had $100.00
in the Department of Public Works Equipment Fund
and it said, expended year to date was a 100,000.
So we'd already gone through the full amount that was budgeted by
>> October of last year. Is that accurate? That is accurate. We refund we put a 100,000
in.
We added a little back to the fund because we sold several older pieces of equipment.
And then this year, we basically bought a bobcat,
or a skid steer for the town. So we added that. That was approved by CIP.
That was around 75,000
and what was left
after adding money back in for the sale of older equipment plus what was put into the fund
netted around 45,000.
>> So that's about what's in the account right now? Correct. Thank you. Correct.
>> And we had originally anticipated spending this money in next year's budget
and we would have asked you for approval right now
for the purchase
but we would not have actually
had to write a check until last next year,
next budget season
but because the manufacturers
have so few build spots,
they're basically they can force us to escrow the money,
for the first payment, which is what they're doing.
Of the questions that somebody do that. I'll second it.
Before
>> we are there any other questions related to this ballot question?
Do we actually change it on here?
>> You don't have to change it on your form as long as you vote in. Okay.
I'm sure they'll accept that.
Okay. This vote is just on the amendment.
>> So
about six months ago, the time town applied for
and was awarded a steep grant.
And the purpose of the steep grant
was to replace the old firehouse at 15 Center Street with a new parking structure
for
senior transportation
because one of the issues we ran into with locating the community center where it was
was we didn't really covered storage for
senior transportation.
So, the way this works is the town agrees to contribute about $75.00
to the multi use building fund which will leave that fund with approximately
$350,000
in it.
And this is not going to affect the funding for the construction of the community slash senior center. That
center is funded using the American Rescue Plan Act funds,
and it is fully funded.
So
this this project basically requires
asbestos and lead abatement of the existing building,
demolition,
and then construction of the new structure.
This is the existing
building
right here,
and
this is the proposed parking garage that we're building.
So one of the reasons why we chose the location that we did is because that location has available three phase power.
And as many of you know, the states are pushing municipalities
really hard to electrify the fleet. What this allows us is this allows us an area
where we have
the ability to install
DC fast chargers because we have three phase power available.
Are we gonna build it when we build the buildings? No.
But we're going to
put in pre phase power to the building so that when we
if we do end up getting an electric bus or something of that nature, we have the ability to charge it right there
in its location.
That location
at 15 Center Street
also would serve in the future as the depot for the bus
because like a lot of institutions,
GATCO, who's our bus service provider,
is getting pushed very hard for
electrifying
bus fleets
and
the where the buses are stored right now is in the floodplain,
and there's no way we're getting building permit
permission
to put,
you know, very expensive electrical devices in the floodplain.
So the one one of the rationales for using
this location
is it allows us a future location for
rapid charging buses.
So that's basically what we're doing.
So the next question is will,
you know, will we accept that grant
application from the state or that grant from the state?
And
happy to answer any questions.
So what is the square footage
>> of this new apartment building?
It's basically 36 by 60.
And the other thing I didn't mention before
is that we're building the top, because we're building this into the bank,
we have we have the ability to have walk in access
from the upper level
into the upper area.
So, this will be built with the floor strong enough that it can take, you know, we can use it for storage which is something the town desperately needs.
>> So, will any of our fire equipment or our fire trucks fit into this in these larger bays or no?
>> So those are good questions.
Part of the reason we did this aesthetically was to try as best as we could to fit into the neighborhood. As you know, Center Street's a pretty eclectic neighborhood. There's no real common design theme.
There's some capes. There's some colonials. There's some things that I would describe as kind of a mishmash.
So we're trying to make it look appropriate to the neighborhood even though it is a parking garage.
This
faces
the lower portion of Center Street. So if you looked at the backside of this building, you would see it is a blank wall. There are no cables on the back, and that is done because the back faces pretty well solar south,
and that would be a prime location
for solar on this building. And the trusses are are specked on this building
so that solar is not a problem be added.
Well, the
this space of the roof right here, the base that you're looking at right now, base is pretty much to north. Yeah. And it's about a six and ten
pitch.
So it would not be a candidate for solar anyway because the solar gain would be too low.
Same all the way across because you needed to use that for the bus or not?
Any loss? Well,
to be honest, we kind of figured it's unlikely
that we're gonna need three buses,
you know, or more than three buses for senior transportation,
which is why we decided to save a few bucks and have one, you know, smaller scale door.
I mean, we could. We could make them all fall, but that's a pretty big cost adder, believe it or not. So
>> this is located in the historic district in Andover? Yes, it is. And
is this aesthetically
meet
that architectural
piece of
being historic?
Historical,
will the
contractors who did this job
have to do something to make it look a little bit more
historical like
historic district requires?
>> So there is no specific
requirement
for aesthetics
in a historical district other than what we as townspeople set.
Mhmm. So
we do have to jump through the hoops because
that building, believe it or not, is on the historic register. Yeah. We
did
I did walk through it with SHPO,
which is the State Historical Preservation Office.
So
because their first impression anytime you tell them you're taking down a historic building is like, no. No. No. We can't do that.
And then we walked through the building and they're like, yeah. You can take this one down.
There
will be some
we're going to try to use demolition contractor that preserves
some of the old chestnut beans because there are some hand hewn chestnut beans and we probably ought to not just throw them in the dumpster.
And the bar to happy
is going to have to do some
basically, state law says anytime you take down a historical structure, no matter how trash it is, you have to do something to mitigate that.
So So, we're probably looking at a a some repairs to the Andover Museum which was the old Andover Town Hall.
They're needed anyway because the doors are completely rotten in the building.
So we're gonna do a bunch of things we've had on our punch list for a long time anyway
to satisfy
the state historical preservation office
>> and to get them to officially approve of us demolishing this building. And just to end my question, siding, what type of siding is going on it and
light siding and lighting, it can look somewhat
historical.
Has that been considered yet or that's part of the bid process?
>> So, we did spec a vinyl siding for this building just for low maintenance.
You know, obviously, if the public really wants some other kind of siding, we can certainly consider it.
But given that there's no really coherent theme
in that area, I really don't wanna put wood siding on something that's a garage.
But we're not leaving exposed concrete either.
I mean, this is designed to be a fairly aesthetic building. You
know, and and obviously, these are
you know, they will add a little light to the 2nd Floor, but they're mainly just there as decoration,
so it looks appropriate in the zone.
We looked at a whole bunch of different
barn like structures
and compared them to what was in that area
before,
but there's really no common theme there that we can really match exactly.
So, we picked this as being a reasonable compromise.
Mary?
>> It will not.
That's already a five or six year old, actually closer to ten year old
ductless split AC.
Given the cost of a new unit, it's not worth trying to recycle something that's already that age because what you would have to do is you would have to
essentially uninstall it, take your refrigerant out,
and that's a refrigerant that's
not as common today anyway.
So we looked at that and the cost of doing it just aren't it'd be nice if we could recycle it, but we really can't. Yeah. It's older, but we really didn't use it that much, but
forward.
You know, whether you want it at the new community center or whether you have another area you have picked out for it but we're we're definitely not growing that one away.
I mean
Let's it approved first and then
>> You know, I'm happy to work with whoever we end up with as a contractor on this to to try to make it as aesthetic as possible.
You know?
>> Similar question, where is the multiuse building fund in the budget?
And you said there's about
there will be about $3.25 left in it. Is that accurate?
That is accurate. There's roughly
>> Is that the 500,000 that initially was a fund gathered through the community center? There was there it was
>> so the town put money away starting five or six years ago to build the community center. And we had to be building that slowly.
We got basically a big infusion of cash
from the ARPA funds.
And the ARPA funds were enough to fund the complete construction cost of the building.
So the Board of Selectmen,
you know, to spend the ARPA funds on that, and that gets us up to the million dollar threshold. We don't want to exceed anyway
because it bumps us up into paying
prevailing wage.
So we're trying
you know, we we basically are keeping the cost under 1,000,000 anyway,
so we're fully funded. So, yes, that money was originally put aside as a multi use building fund,
but it was understood that the project we were putting it away for was the community center.
So, we know we can fund the community center out of existing money.
So, the the one thing we couldn't fund at least that at that point was a decent home for senior transportation.
So, we're going to take part of the money to do that
center,
you know, we can, you know, if we wait six months,
we can spend that money or some of that money on outfitting the community center and not having to have to worry about playing prevailing
>> wage on the whole job. So, that's essentially what we're trying to do. But my initial question was where does the fund appear in the budget? Because again, I'm looking at documents from last October and I don't see either a function
or an indication of the multi use building
fund.
>> Right, we did not fund the multi use building fund. We put nothing in the fund last year because
by last year we knew we had hard work funds so we didn't fund it last year. But
would show up in the budget
budget in the transfer section.
>> If I wanted to, which I do, obviously, how do I find out how much are in all the they're about six or eight different funds referred to in four different questions here. How does a citizen find out how much is in each of these funds? If it's not in the budget, where do you find out about that? The town audit every year will show up. But we haven't done the audit until most recently. Is that correct? Go to last year's audit. I did. And you're saying it's not in last year's audit? What I'm saying is is
audit was just completed. Is that correct?
>> Yes. Okay. So prior to the audit, if I wanted to know, do I have to do audit amount about six or ten months after the budget year to find out? No, you could go to last year's to find out what was there and then you would add, in this case there wasn't any added in the standing budget so you would have no additions.
And then for spending, normally we'd have a monthly
outlay. Obviously you know the town has had some issues with staff turnover in that office.
So, you know, they're actually working on transitioning to a new software system. So they're a little behind on those budgets, but they are those monthly budgets. But once those get caught up, then we'll have something to
>> Well, I'm just saying that
word that I now hate which is transparency.
I did in fact go here for this meeting and I tried to look at budgets and funds and whatnot.
It's very difficult to find out. We're being asked to move to funds what's in the funds. That's
>> a comment. Coral will get you the audit from the prior year and then we'll get you the Oh, it's on the website. The audit's
now on the website. It is in there? Yep. I didn't I found that, Jess. Thank you. You're welcome. So you did find the information, but you're looking for monthly transfers?
Pardon? You're looking for a monthly transfer or something out of that? I'm just looking for a monthly accounting
>> because the most recent accounting on the town's website is October of last year with regard to the budget.
So,
I don't know if the board of I looked in the board of finances, agenda,
minutes, and the packet that they received
and the most recent packet that was on the website is from last October.
Okay.
Thank you.
>> That links the school and the community center to the rail trail
and get people off of 316
for cycling and for walking.
That's basically what this grant does.
The reason we're applying for a study grant first
is because we know there's gonna be some public opposition, there's no question.
We also wanna look at what the best routes to do this are,
and so by funding a study grant first,
we get public input,
public meetings,
and
the preliminaries
and a basic engineering assessment
of how we get across Staddle Brook.
Currently Staddle Brook is a problem because the
road that goes across is on a 100 plus year old stone bridge,
it's rated a two for functionality,
but the state's not gonna replace it because they say it's an old stone bridge and they don't want to.
So
that's why we're doing it. If you get this grant,
we have a funding mechanism
to actually get it built called LOTZIP.
It's actually one of the few things the town of Andover can actually fund through the Lotsip program.
Our problem as a town
is that
we don't have any roads that are classified as major collectors,
and major collectors up are the roads that normal lots of funding can be solicited for.
So even though it's one of the best funding sources out there
for roadwork, it's something that we're locked out of as a town.
So this is the study group. This is where we are right here. I know this is kinda hard to see. The town owns this parcel right here.
This is Route 316.
This is Sider Mill Road.
This is Senator Street.
So we're basically saying we don't know what the best way to connect those two is.
We think it's gonna be to run it down
the DOT right away in Route 316,
but we don't wanna commit to that until we've looked at all the alternatives.
So that is the question. Do we apply for the grant?
The
statement was a little wishy washy as to where we're gonna fund this from,
and part of that is the logical place to take this money is the open space fund.
However, that requires the approval of the planning and zoning commission.
And frankly, we're not gonna bother. I'm not gonna go through the process of asking until I know I actually have the grant money.
If we didn't, you know, we would probably fund it out of contingency.
It's not gonna affect taxation directly.
We're not talking about spending money we don't we haven't already budgeted for.
Again, I'll open it up for any questions if anybody has it.
>> Could you go back to the map, please, Eric?
Where is Staddlebrook
on this map?
>> Okay. So, Staddlebrook and Route 316 intersects
right by
So basically, there's a number of possible ways this connection can be made.
We're not trying to pick one at this point. We're saying we need to figure out what the best way to do. We know what the problem is,
but we're asking for money to figure out what the solution is.
Other questions?
>> Where is the school?
Is it adjacent to that townhome piece that you have in a slightly
>> different color? This is the school right here. Okay.
So
the goal is to figure out how to develop a path
to right here, which is municipal complex. Right?
And the advantage of here is that that puts you on School Road, which has a direct connection
to Lake Road which is the highest density district.
And then get people from here without going on Route 316
which has no shoulders and some pretty appalling sight lines which we've asked the DOT to correct multiple times and they've called us the pound sand
and get them down to the rail trail. And
the reason we're doing that is the rail trail is basically the non motorized
East West connection
through the town.
It's safe, it's walkable, bikeable horses,
you name it. But the question is, people either have to drive to get to it or they need some
safe way to walk to it or bike to it, and this is part of our efforts.
And by the way, this was
originally proposed
in the plan of conservation and development in 2015,
and it's also part of the Complete Streets Master Plan that the town has for making the town more bikeable and walkable.
So how long of a path is this?
>> Is it a mile? Is it two miles?
It's less than a mile,
and it depends on
how we do it basically.
So there's different options but all the options are gonna be less than a mile.
Submitted a map for such a big study area
because we're not trying to tell them
that
they have to go down 316.
We're putting 316
in the area so that they'll study that,
but we're also saying right up front that the town owns all of this land
back here.
The the problem the town has is when you get up to where the trail is there,
there's some extremely steep grades there.
And that's really hard to overcome without some really extensive switchbacking.
And it's still not something that's
going up 316 is a lot more gradual,
and following alongside of Mill Road is even way more gradual than that.
So if you want something that people are gonna actually use
now, as an avid cyclist, do I care? No. I mean, I'd go up 316 but a lot of people won't. So, our goal is to come up with the easiest route possible so it's used a lot. No sense having a path if people don't take it.
Sir?
Well, that lane way from here. Pool going on. Right. But that lane way
is the gas line.
Okay. I understand what you're talking about. Now that is private property. That we don't own that.
So and since somebody's actively developing that as a farm, I don't think they're gonna be too excited about us running a pathway through the middle of it. But if you note sorry.
If you notice, we expanded
this definition
way past
the boundaries of town property
because we wanted to take in every possibility,
including potentially
going down School Road,
you know, cutting across the dam without POBA's permission and going in that way too. I mean, we're we're open to any consideration
within that range. We just we know what we're trying to do. We're not telling
you know, saying at this point how we wanna do it.
>> Rural improvement program trip
grant proposal
for up to $800,000
which
will require the payment by the town
of survey and engineering costs
estimated
to be
do
the
state of
gonna
that. That.
>> Funding mechanism for roads
is a program called locket, and we're just not eligible
because small towns often don't have roads with enough traffic
to be considered major collectors.
I have tried in the past to nominate some of our roads to the DOT and say we think this one really is a major collector
and we made them come out and do traffic counts and they say yeah, no. So
they put this grant program together to address that
and they
and it unfortunately has a lot of the same requirements as the trip program.
So basically what we're talking about doing
is
putting a grant together for something under $1,000,000.
I originally said $800,000.
That price might climb a little bit,
but if it does, it does not affect you as the taxpayer.
That's just how much the actual grant is.
What the town's gonna have to contribute is the engineering work
to satisfy
the DOT that we're actually competent to reclaim and repave the road.
So that is gonna be somewhere in the neighborhood of $330,000.
I don't have an exact figure for you.
We've talked to our in house engineering firm as
and I bounced off one of the other transportation
engineers that I'm friends with. So I'm pretty sure that our total design costs are gonna be somewhere in that neighborhood.
So what is this gonna allow us to do?
So
just to orient you,
this is Henry Road right here.
This is Long Hill. So this is stuff that's taking place in the northern half of the town,
and roughly three years from now,
the bridge at Long Hill is gonna get replaced.
So for about a year,
there's gonna be no driving up Long Hill.
That means every bit of traffic
to this whole
section,
a whole northern section of the town is gonna be coming up Henley.
Now the first part of Henley is already in pretty good shape,
so what we're proposing to do
is
first address the drainage with public works this summer,
and then starting as soon as we have grant funding,
repave
or first reclaim and then repave
the section
all the way up to Wheeling Road so that at the point where
we're forced to just use this,
we have a road that's more capable of handling the traffic.
As a lot of you know, we drove it up until last year. It was in really bad shape.
We did shim and
chip seal it as a temporary measure,
but the underlying road structure is pretty bad.
So that's in a nutshell what we're trying to do. We looked at projects in a couple different parts of town,
but we picked one we thought that was most likely to be funded.
So that's basically what we're doing and why we're going after that.
And that is the question.
Are you saying later that Long will be Can you speak up? After the bridge? You gotta speak up. I'm a little deaf. Will will you say,
are we planning to do redo Long Hill after we do the bridge?
Well,
we just spent a half $1,000,000
reclaiming and repaving the first section of Long Hill, so we're not doing anything more to that section. How about the chip seal part?
So
I would like to,
but
the reality is reclaiming and repaving the road right now
is somewhere in the order of a half million dollars
per mile,
and we've got 34 miles of roadway in the town of Andover.
So unless you all wanna pass a 17 or $18,000,000
bond package,
we're not gonna do a lot of reclaiming and repaving
unless
we can get grant money to do it. The way we were able to do that section of Long Hill and also Shawnee Mill is because we had a previous state grant that we
sought and were awarded that offset part of the cost of doing that.
Yeah. Roadwork today is just kinda crazy expensive.
Yep. That's
>> the sole extent we're gonna be able to do out of this rent funding. Be
nice if we can do a lot more. I agree. But we can't how long again, how long the stretch
is that is that rough?
The portion
that would
>> So all all of Hending gonna gonna be be be redone? Done?
>> Not all of Hendy.
The very first part of Hendy basically up to Pine Ridge is not gonna be redone
because that portion of the road
was,
re done much sooner
and it doesn't have a pavement condition index
low enough
for us to be able to apply to to redo that section of the road.
So
what is the distance of the road that's gonna be?
I
think
that engineers being optimists
tell us that it's
should not take more than nine months,
but they also told me it should only take two years to,
get to do Bunker Hill,
and the state is still arguing with the design contractor over that one.
So, yeah, I I think planning on
that bridge being out of commission for a year is realistic.
I don't want it any longer because that's my commute every day too.
That's the last thing I want.
Rich?
14 no, one blank.
That also passed.